Inventory of the Virginia Council on Human Relations Papers 1960-1966
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Virginia Council on Human Relations Papers, 1960-1966.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 68 V82
ca. 150 items, 1 box.
Records of the Virginia Council on Human Relations and the Southern Education Fund, 1960-1966. Pamphlets, booklets, reports, newsletters, correspondence, clippings relating to school desegregation, fair employment practices, housing, etc.
Virginia Council on Human Relations,; Southern Conference Educational Fund.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: ca. 150 items, 1966.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Council on Human Relations was a private organization formed to encourage better race relations. There were chapters in various localities and its headquarters was in Richmond.
Scope and Content Information
The Virginia Council on Human Relations (VCHR) was a non-profit organization that attempted to find resolutions to the "race problem," i.e., school desegregation, fair employment practices, housing, inter- cultural relations, public facility desegregation, voting rights and registration) in the state of Virginia. Stressing both constructive solutions and cooperative action, the VCHR worked with the Southern Regional Council and with Councils on Human Relations in other Southern states to realize its goal of acknowledging and accepting the "Legitimate aspirations of all the people of Virginia," regardless of race, color, or national origin.
The VCHR Papers represent an assortment of documents that chronicles the activities of the Council between 1960 and 1966. Part of the VCHR Papers contain leaflets, booklets, and pamphlets that outlines the goals, objectives, and purposes of the VCHR. Another portion of the Paper consists of official letters from key Council representatives to either members of local VCHR branches or to Southern citizens who support the VCHR. Printed documents of the Southern Conference Educational Fund, Inc., or SCEF (i.e., The Southern Patriot, newspaper of the SCEF, letters of Fred Shuttleworth, president of SCEF) and the Southern Regional Council are a part of the VCHR Papers. Official "Minutes" records, financial reports, newsletters, and memos of the VCHR are also a part of the assorted collection that is the VCHR Papers. Finally, the VCHR Papers contain documents from the Norfolk, Fairfax, and other Virginian branches of the VCHR.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into folders by subject.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Race relations--Virginia.; African Americans-- Segregation--Southern States.; Virginia--Race relations.
Organization Names:
Southern Conference Educational Fund.
Contents List
- Leaflets, booklets, and letters of the Virginia Council on Human Relations which outline the objectives of the VCHR, 1962-1963., 17 items. (Folder 1)
- Pamphlets, booklets, and letters from Southern chapters of the Virginia council on Human Relations, 1957-1965., 12 items. PDs. (Folder 2)
- Schedules, memo, and letters of the Virginia Council on Human Relations that outline dates and events of the VCHR, 1963., 17 items. TDs. (Folder 3)
- Leaflets and typed documents of the Southern Conference Educational Fund, Inc. that outline their purpose, 1963-1965., 11 items. PDs. (Folder 4)
- The Southern Patriot, the newspaper of the Southern Conference Educational Fund, Inc., 1963-1965., 7 items. Nwss. (Folder 5)
- Letters of Fred L. Shuttleworth, President of the Southern Conference Educational Fund, Inc. to "friends of Civil Rights.", 1963-1965., 7 items. TLsS. (Folder 6)
- Memo and typed documents that detail the plans of the Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1961-1962., 9 items. TDs. (Folder 7)
- Financial and budget reports of the Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1961-1963., 10 items. TDs. (Folder 8)
- Minutes, resolutions, and reports of the Virginia Council on Human Relations., 13 items. TDs. (Folder 9)
- Minutes, letters, and typed documents of the Equal Job Opportunities Committee of the VCHR that summarizes their goals and objectives, 1962-1964., 14 items. TDs. (Folder 10)
- Minutes, resolutions, and reports of the Virginia Council on Human Relations that address the plans and the objectives of the VCHR, 1963-1965., 35 items. TDs. (Folder 11)
- Financial reports of the Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1963-1964., 8 items. TDs. (Folder 12)
- Memos and typed documents that summarize the activities of the Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1965-1966., 17 items. TDs. (Folder 13)
- Newsletter of the Virginia Council on Human Relations, 1964-1966., 10 items. PDs. (Folder 14)
- Paper clippings from Richmond newspaper, 1962-1963., 6 items. NwsCls. (Folder 15)
- Paper clippings from The Washington Post, 1963-1964., 2 items. NwsCls. (Folder 16)
- Paper clippings from The News, Lynchburg, Virginia, February 1963., 2 items. NwsCls. (Folder 17)
- Southern Regional Council pamphlets that focus on the subject of school desegregation, 1961., 2 items. PDs. (Folder 18)